Hello, welcome. It is May
22nd,
2025. We are in active inference
gueststream
108.1 discussing next generation
artificial intelligence for emergent
semantic communications with Christo K.
Thomas. So Kristoff, thank you very much
for joining. Looking forward to hearing
about the work and also to everyone's
comments and questions from the live
chat. Thank you to you.
Thanks Daniel for the introduction. Um
yeah and thank you for inviting me for
this talk. Um so I'll be talking about u
next generation um artificial
intelligence for emerging semantic
communication and also uh I would like
to express my gratitude to my
collaborators my postto advisor Dr.
Walit Sad and uh PhD student in our
group Omar Hash. Um yeah so I would also
like to advertise a bit on uh the
upcoming research group I will be
establishing as a tenot track assistant
professor at Worster Polytechnic
Institute in Massachusetts. Uh so
therein uh my focus will be uh to work
at the intersection of next generation
artificial intelligence and wireless
systems uh with specific focus on uh
resilient and interoperable semantic
communication and integrated sensing and
communication frameworks. Uh explainable
and generalizable AI for next generation
wireless systems. foundation models for
networking applications and uh
developing strong mathematical
foundations of cognitive and reasoning
driven a
architectures. So yeah, so this is an
outline of the talk. Um so first I will
go over a motivation of next generation
a native wireless networks. Um which is
uh yeah so then further I will talk
about two of my recent research work on
semantic communication and further I
will uh provide some future perspectives
uh which involve emerging language
design and uh using active
inference. Um so yeah so so if you look
at the wireless evolution right now we
are at the fifth generation of wireless
systems which promised apart from you
know cellular uh enhancing the cellular
communication
um aspects like massive machine type of
communication or ultra reliable low
latency communication. Uh however 5G
could not meet all the promises it uh
actually made. Um so yeah as like the
you know saying goes usually the odd
generation oddnumbered generations are
not very successful at their uh what
they promise. So if that is true so
usually you know the even number of
generation so next one will be the 6G.
So we can expect more exciting
developments in uh sixth generation of
wireless systems. Um so in 60 so we are
not okay as we move towards making our
environments more smarter through know
making the network intelligent uh and be
able to control the actions of uh
distant autonomous agents in the
environment.
uh so in order to support those
applications 6G brings in lot of uh diff
more distinct set of challenges like
know trustworthiness security and
resilience of underlying AI models
immersivity sensing a nativity and
sustainable computing. So here uh AI is
going to play a crucial role in the know
design management or um maintenance of
different network and device functions.
So yeah so such a transition from the
fifth generation to a native sixth
generation um is expected as we move to
sixth generation of technologies. So
here the question is why AI native
because it can brings in the aspects of
know adaptability to dynamically varying
uh wireless environment or tasks. It can
handle nonlinear signals. Uh it can also
bring in lot of resource efficiency uh
compared to classical systems. So these
are some of the advantages that a
nativity provides. However, if you look
at the state-ofthe-art of a native
networks, so currently the literature is
predominantly datadriven a algorithms
like you know uh so uh yeah metal laning
or autoenccoders, CNN's and right now at
know there is a huge hype on using large
language models for uh wireless uh
network optimization. However, these
datadriven machine learning algorithms
are plagued by the following
disadvantages like uh yeah large data
size which is required which which may
not be always available readily in a
wireless systems. Second is their
limited generalizability to changing
wireless environments or task. Uh so
yeah associated with the limited general
service aspect that we need frequent
retraining of these machine learning
models which means we yeah if if you
have to build know communication I mean
real time communication and control such
datadriven machine learning algorithms
are not suitable. So another aspect is
they they act like blackbox models. So
they lack interpretability and then they
require huge computing power. So you
know unsustainable computing uh is
another disadvantage of these machine
learning algorithms. So as we transition
from the current a native to next
generation a native we must advance
artificial intelligence together with
the wireless network uh evolution. So
that's the focus of few of our research
papers regress vision papers that we um
uh some I mean that got accepted in the
last couple of years. Uh so one paper in
in one in one paper we actually
discussed how how we can actually used
next generation machine learning
algorithms like causal reasoning for um
diverse um or cross-layer network
optimization task. And another paper
that actually got accepted at the IT
proceedings of IT, we actually looked at
a rigorous artificial general
intelligence um based vision. Um which I
will summarize as
follows. So yeah, so next generation
wireless systems are not just about
communication. So this those will also
involve lot of sensing. So sensing act
like an eye for the network. So using
the sensed information that contains the
states of different autonomous agents or
cyber physical systems in the
environment the network should then act
like a telecom brain. So where telecom
brain is characterized by distinct um
capabilities such as perception which
means the ability to generate abstract
representations about different semantic
concepts present in the data. then using
these abstractions to perform or to
compute or learn a world model that
actually allows it to understand the
cause and effect relations among
different physical processes in the
world. So this world model will allow it
to perform or predictions about future
networks or environment states and then
use that predictions to basically
perform action planning on the network.
So here action planning refers to not
just network actions like you know
resource allocation or beam forming but
also u designing optimal control actions
uh for the autonomous agents in the
environment so as to you know guide or
know control them um in the way as that
the network intend it to perform. So
that's the idea of the know telecom
brain principle um that we actually
envision. So along this direction uh one
aspect is the perception or the semant
extracting semantics from the data. So
further in this talk I'll be talking
about know how we can um extracting
semantics and then communicating this
semantics how it can actually enhance
the resource efficiency of next
generation wireless system. So that will
be the focus of the um uh next few
slides. So to introduce semantic
communication. So if you look at the
classical communication view uh so
therein the objective was to know ensure
that the messages are recovered at the
receiver side with the arbitrary low
probability of error as possible. So
that is the technical problem. So while
doing so we have so far ignored the
semantic aspect which means what meaning
do these transmitted symbols convey and
the effectiveness problem which means
how effectively does the received
meaning affect conduct in the desired
way at the receiver side. So yeah as
Shannon has also mentioned the semantic
aspects are irrelevant to the
engineering problem. However, when we
move towards future networks wherein we
need um we we have lot of stringent
communication requirements as well as
lot of other you know intelligent
requirements like you know
trustworthiness or immersivity as I
discussed before uh we cannot continue
to rely on just the technical problem.
So in order to make the communication
resources more efficient uh we must
transition to a novel paradigm called
semantic communication. So in semantic
communication the objective is to
transmit the meaning behind the
messages. So here meaning actually means
only the information that is relevant to
the end user. So communicate this
information relevant information by
building a semantic language between the
transmitter and receiver. We call the
transmitter to be a teacher and
apprentice receiver to be an apprentice.
So yeah, so by creating a machine
language
um the objective is to ensure that
perceiver is able to regenerate the
meaning uh with high fidelity as
possible. So here the question is so
what is this semantic semantics actually
contained in the uh data. Um so yeah so
if you look at the
state-ofthe-art one traditional
framework is this join source channel
coding frame framework. So, so in
traditional system we used to separate
the source encoding and the channel
encoding part. But in join source
channel coding framework we actually
combine the source and channel encoding
to one module. And in deep joint source
channel coding we use a machine learning
in based encoder and decoder and then
train them in an end to end fashion with
the goal of minimizing certain semantic
loss function. So by training such
machine learning models we achieve we we
ensure that transmitter extract only the
relevant information or relevant
features from the data and communicate
that information only. So that leads to
better compression uh in terms of what
is being communicated. However our
vision is that semantic communication is
not just about you know compressing
better compressing the data. So instead
so if you can instill machine reasoning
at the know transmitter and receiver
side let's say receiver has better re I
mean u you know prediction capabilities
or uh ability to you know generate u
missing information so which can be
achieved through know instilling
advanced machine learning framework. Uh
so then we can achieve more minimalism
in communication compared to just doing
deep joint source channel coding and
then if we can instill these
generalizable machine learning
algorithms that actually ensure that
these we don't need to retrain the
system as tasks or the wireless
environment changes. So that is also
very crucial for enabling real time
communication and control and another
goal is to ensure high fidelity at the
receiver side. So in my previous work I
have so far tackled these three
challenges which I will talk about in
detail and but there are also other open
challenges like how to ensure
interoperable multi-user semantic system
when each of the users speak different
semantic
languages or how to build a resilient
semantic communication system. So
resilience against any network
disruptions that could be due to uh time
varying channel conditions or cyber
attacks and then how to integrate these
SC principles into the current 3GPP
standards without introducing
significant interoperability and
standardization challenges. So those are
some open problems that I am currently
looking at. uh uh yeah so let me first
talk about uh my uh first work on
semantics that got uh published in IT
transactions on wireless communication.
So this is about building a reasoning
foundation for emergent semantic
communication. So in particular I
consider a two two user semantic
communication system. So wherein the
transmitter um observes the world state
and extracts the entities present in the
data and then using the entities
extracted it computes a semantic state
description which I will talk about in
later a detail later which is okay
denoted by isert belonging to syntactic
space and then the syntactic space I
mean isert is encoded uh to a
representation space and then
communicated at the receiver. Receiver
extracts a semantic state. Using the
extracted semantic state, receiver
performs certain reasoning which is
denoted by five of set hat. And this
recent output is used to perform certain
actions on the world state. So here
there are two problems that I consider.
So one is the reasoning problem. So
which involves how to learn the
semantics present in the data or how to
define these semantics and at the
receiver after reconstructing the
semantic state how the receiver can
perform deductive reasoning and given
this deductive reasoning how the know
transmitter can um better encode this
enode is another problem which is the
emergent language problem. So wherein at
the start of communication transmitter
is not aware of how the what are the
semantics that receiver is interested in
and the receiver is not aware of how the
transmitter is in which language that
the transmitter will be going to encode
the semantics. So learning this encoder
and decoder those are which are
formulated as you know probabilist
probability distribution given as shown
here pi of u given is and pi of given x
comma c here actually corresponds to the
communication context. So that will be
the history of semantics that
communicated in the previous time
instance. So that is the emergent
language
problem. Yeah. So for so so for the
reasoning framework uh we use uh
causality from machine learning. So
where causality is founded on three
different principles. So one is the
cosal discovery. So given the uh you
know entities present in the data. So
here we call these entities as semantic
content elements. So only those entities
that are really relevant for the end
user task. So those those are the
semantic content elements. So we learn
the cosign effect relations between
these entities as a directed as cyclic
graph as is shown here. So from
causality literature this can be called
as the structural causal model and the
structural cosal models apart from these
semantic content elements it could also
involve certain exogenous random
variables that are actually uh unknown
or hidden from the um uh hidden from us.
Yeah. So that's a causal discovery
phase. So second phase is the cosal
representation learning. So, so when we
are given a large dimensional
observation, maybe it could be large
dimensional antenna measurements. So, we
it may not be immediately available be
known to us what are the cosal cause and
effect variables. So, we need to first
convert it to a lower dimensional latent
representation involving just the causal
variables. So, that is the cosal
representation learning part. So do you
so during this causal representation
learning phase we can actually filter
out the relevant and irrelevant
variables from the um features extracted
from the data. Then finally we have the
causal inference phase. So wherein if
you are given this causal graph we can
perform intervention that actually mean
we can manipulate the values of certain
endogenous variables here then analyze
what is the impact that cause on their
effect variables. And then we can also
perform counterfactuals that means so
given we have observed certain set of
entities as shown here. So what would
the world stage would be if these know
let's say S4 if you want if you if you
want to imagine different outcome for
S4. So what what interventions on these
causes would have caused that. So such
imaginary words we can assume using the
framework of counterfactuals. So if we
can actually okay extract this causal
graph and then perform training on this
interventional and counterfactual
distribution then we can actually attain
a level of distribution generalization.
So that's the advantage of bringing in
cosality and another thing is the
explanability aspect that so given this
cosal graph we can actually tell like
you know uh if you have a cosal graph uh
among uh distinct environment variables
then resource allocation communication
and computing resource allocation
variables and quality of service values
then we can actually assess if the
performance falls below certain
threshold. So what are the underlying
causes that actually lead led to that
particular behavior? So that that's
where this explanability aspect is uh
coming by using the framework of
causality. So now uh okay so using the
cosal framework we learn the cosal graph
from the data. So learning the cosal
graph we formulate it as a factorized
posterior distribution where each factor
will be the probability of each of these
node variables given the its parent. So
probability of s1 given probability of
so probility s1 given s0 where s0 is the
parent of s1. So that probability
distribution we can use we we learn
using a recently popular a method called
generative flow networks wherein we
start with an unconnected set of
entities and iteratively learn each urge
starting from this unconnected set of
entities and then at the receiver side
after receiving this causal state
receiver actually combines these smaller
states and then perform a logical
reasoning where this logical reasoning
is performed by evaluating certain
logical formula which is composed of
these causal states that are connected
by certain logical connective. So it's
like evaluating. So okay if this
happened uh if the set of okay if these
are the set of um I mean if this is the
causal state that the transmitter has
observed okay then what would happen in
the future. Okay. Yeah. So those kind of
reasoning or inferences can be um
performed using this logical inference
uh framework. So for that we use neuro
symbolic AI. we cannot uh so we we use a
existing neurosyic a method called
logical neural network that actually
converts this logical formula to a
neural network. Uh yeah so that's how we
actually perform the logical reasoning
at the receiver
side. So now uh yeah I will
uh yeah I will consider the I will
discuss the emergent language problem.
So, so in the emerging language problem,
the teacher's objective is to ensure
that it communicates very less semantic
information as feasible. Uh so trans
yeah the transmitter is kind of uh u
yeah so that's the goal of transmitter.
Uh so which is formulated as negative of
average semantic information uh at the
transmitter side. So semantic
information conveyed by the transmit
semantic symbol U about the causal state
uh is said given the policy given the
enor policy as well as the history of
causal states at the receivers side
receivers's objective is to maximize the
reconstructed semantic information. Uh
so after receiving U how much
information that can provide about the
causal state is it had D which is the
reconstructed one given the policy of
transmitter as well as the uh policy of
the receiver and the history of causal
states
reconstructed with the then there are
certain constraints like you know
communication cost plus u minus log pt
which is an apprentice surprise factor.
So which actually tells us how much the
apprentices surprised after receiving
certain semantic information. So yeah.
So here given this contrasting
objectives of teacher and apprentice we
can formulate this as a two-player
signaling game and the Nash equilibrium
of this two-player signaling game is uh
can be formulated as is shown here. So
yeah like apprentice responding to the
um given the know teachers optimal
encoder policies what's the best
response that actually you know
apprentice can uh provide that's that
that's what this expression actually
tells us so we actually solves this
through a since given so we actually
formulated novel semantic information
measures for the transmit side and
receive side but we observed that those
are non-convex functions so we solved
them through an alternating optimization
procedure where alternating optimization
is performed for some surrogate
functions that are convex. So yeah, so
this actually evolves this game evolves
through a two-way conversation between
teacher and the apprentice wherein
apprentice asks certain questions about
the data set data and teacher responds
by providing an encoded version of the u
information. So that's how this game
actually proceeds.
So as I mentioned here we cannot
continue to rely on the traditional
mutual information measures since we
need to quantify uh semantic information
here. So as I mentioned here
uh how I formulate semantic information
is that so semantic information is
formulated as the information contained
in the logical endailments or logical
conclusions that follow from any causal
state. For example, if you look at any
word like red, there are multiple
possibilities conclusion that can follow
from it like know red blooded or red
ruby, red meat and so on. So those
conclusions the information can load
into those conclusions that are relevant
to the end user. So that will be the
semantic information. So we actually
analytically formulate this from a
category theory perspective where we uh
what we did is we form we defined a
syntax category consisting of coal
states as the object and a semantics
category consisting of the conclusion
that follow from any cosal state and
cooperives corresponds to from a
category theory perspectives corresponds
to the uh you know conclusions or how we
yeah conclusions that follow from any
causal state in the syntax category and
this logical endance we can map it or we
can consider it as a factor from the
syntax category to the semantic
category. So that's how we actually
formulated this semantic information
measure and we also discussed received
semantic information which can be
written as a fraction of fraction equal
to semantic similarity of the
transmitted information where semantic
similarity can be computed by
quantifying the overlap in terms of the
capriccious of transmitted semantic
causal state and reconstructed causal
state. Yeah. So further uh yeah so
further we perform certain Nash
equilibrium analysis. So wherein we
first did some equilibrium analysis for
some trivial cases like the cardinality
of the representation space is one. So
that actually means we transmit same
semantic symbol for all causal state. So
that is minimalistic but you know
receiver may need may not be able to
reconstruct the meaning with high
fidelity. And we also considered the
separating equilibrium where cardality
of U is same as cardality of W. So that
leads to high fidelity of meaning
reconstruction but it leads to maximal
transmission. So another thing is uh the
partial pooling case where the cardality
of U is less than the cardality of W. So
that leads to a minimal representation
at the same time ensure a high fidelity
sufficiently high fidelity at the
receiver stage. So in this partial
pooling case so some interesting
insights we got. So so we actually um
showed that the the partitioning of the
syntactic space occur in such a way that
we communicate UK for all causal state
that lead to the same semantics at the
receiver side. So this partitioning of
the semantics causal state uh
corresponds to a partitioning in the
semantic space unlike a partitioning in
the equilidian space for traditional
communication
systems. So that's an interesting uh
insight that we got from this N
equilibrium analysis. So further I
conclude this results by know discussing
the summary of key analytical results.
As I mentioned, we formulated novel
semantic information using category
theory. And we also derived our upper
upper and lower bounds of average amount
of bits communicated in an ES emerging
semantic communication system and showed
that these upper and lower bounds are
less than that of a classical system
showing minimalism and we also derived
semantic error probability measures. So
that showed that the lower bound on
semantic error probability is always
less than or equal to the lower bound on
the probability of bit error measure
achieved using classical communication
system. So what that tells us is that so
even if the probability of bitter is may
be high still the receiver may be able
to reconstruct the semantics with high
fidelity as possible. So that means we
can uh it's okay to know we can avoid
these retransmissions as in classical
system and we can maybe transmit at a
lower rate. So that means that we must
transition to semantic performance
measure if we are to make efficient use
of communication resources. So that's
another insight that followed from these
results. So further I would like to
discuss some simulation results. So we
for the simulation we actually looked at
a visual question and answering based
data set where teacher communicates
certain images encoded versions of the
images and then uh apprentices objective
is to uh answer certain questions based
on these images. So we evaluated this uh
the performance of the emergent language
um for different tasks where we started
with a simpler task where the image only
contains maybe one object. So images
here contains objects of different
shape, color and size and we increase
the complexity of this task. So as time
progresses what we saw is that uh the
amount of u communication rounds
required for this emergent language
training reduces close to zero. So that
tells us that uh yeah the system is this
semantic communication system is gaining
more knowledge or receiver uh the
apprentice is gaining more knowledge as
time progresses. uh so then you know
because of this more knowledge it can
actually avoid retraining for the
emerging language so that yeah that way
we can get rid of lot of communication
over uh yeah so that's the
generalizability aspect and we also
evaluated the average amount of bits
communicated over the wireless network
wherein we showed that for our proposed
system we almost gain around 100x gain
compared to classic traditional
semantic communication system that does
not incorporate reasoning into their
architecture and compared to classical
system yeah even much more gain is
obtained. So that actually show shows
the minimalism aspect that I was uh
discussing. So that actually uh
concludes the yeah work on emerging
semantic
communication and next I will briefly
discuss um one followup work that we did
where we utilize this cosal semantic
communication framework for a digital
twin driven wireless network. U yeah so
this got accepted at at channel on
selected areas in information theory. So
here one application is as is shown
here. Let's say we want to control the
operations of certain autonomous robots
in an industrial environment. Um yeah
using the communication from a base
station or an edge server. So herein we
assume that okay given that this
particular industrial environment will
be also uh lot of senses will be
deployed in this environment. So using
the sensed information the base station
actually construct a uh digital twin of
the industrial environment and uses this
digital twin uh it actually you know
using the digital twin it actually
computes optimal control actions uh for
these autonomous robots in the system.
So this is within the framework of
semantic communication system and that's
what I will be discussing here.
So yeah so so here this semantic
communication framework again we
consider for a two user so pointto-point
system wherein the transmitter it's
called an expert agent because it has
access to lot of sensing information and
using the sensed information it creates
a world model about the wireless
environment or autonomous agent
environment uh so basically extract the
semantic content elements and no uh
generate the coal graph and using the
cosal graph it actually computes an
expert policy control policy and at the
and this okay instead of computing the
control policy the transmitter actually
computes a cosal semantic representation
of the cosal graph and the receiver
receiver also has a world model at its
end but it creates this world model from
the limited communicated information and
then it also computes an imit receiver
here is called an imitator because it
tries to compute a policy uh and the
objective is that this policy should be
as close to the expert policy of the
transmitter as possible and this is
achieved using the framework of
imitation learning and that's why it's
called an imitator agent. So that's the
yeah so this policy imitator policy
should be such that it is quite close to
the optimal expert policy. Yeah. so as
to ensure that the semantic
effectiveness of the task at the uh
receiver side is as high as possible. So
that's the system model. So compared to
our previous work here in we went one
step beyond in terms of defining the in
I mean semantic information. So in
traditional uh mutual information
frameworks it does not distinguish
between causal I mean uh directionality
of information like where I of X Y is
basically same as I of Y comma X. So
yeah. So but in in a cosal system we
must be able to distinguish between uh I
of X Y. If X crosses Y uh then yeah I of
X Y should be different when you know uh
when it should be different than I of Y
X. So this is achieved through the
principle of intrinsic information. So
given okay let's say assume that sit is
the state of the system at time t and IC
of sit minus one given sit tells us
about the cause information about the
cause state which is st minus one um
provided by the current state s.
Similarly we can define the effect
information which is basically the
information about the future effect
states. So this can be defined using a
distance measure between these two
probability distribution which is
probability of SIT minus one given SIT
and property of SIT minus one. Similarly
for the effect information and we choose
sustained distance here because of this
um unique properties that you know the
distance is uh symmetric here. So that's
the reason why we actually uh resorted
to sustain distance here and further we
can define the concept of integrated
information. So let's say that this SIT
is composed of distinct semantic content
elements. So okay so our objective is to
basically perform abstractions of this
semantic content elements by you know
filtering out irrelevant states. So we
can how we define integrated information
for a particular state sit is that
integrated information is the
information conveyed um conveyed by uh
the states beyond that of what is
conveyed by the individual semantic
content elements. So that actually means
that only if okay let's say the semantic
content elements are all independent
random variables then there there won't
be any interactions between these
different semantic content elements so
then the integrated information will be
zero. So once there are some
interactions between certain set of
semantic content elements so that that
means that there are some cause and
effect relations between these semantic
content elements. So yeah we so those
set of states will form a a semantic
concept with nonzero integrated
information. So that's how we can
actually uh know define a semantic
concept or extract a semantic or
identify a semantic concept from the
data. So that's one uh you know yeah um
step in terms of advancing the theory of
semantic information
um that we actually proposed in this
work. So further I would also like to
quickly discuss uh the methodology that
we used for. So as I mentioned here we
have to transmitter has to learn the
cosal graph uh so which is achieved
through cosal discovery and also this
cosal graph should be represented
semantically.
It should have a semantic representation
uh which is actually uh represented as
isert t here and then yeah so then then
the transmitter also has to compute a
action control policy which is pi export
of action given the state uh future
state current state as well as uh the
set of sensed variables and then it also
has to come up with this transition
distribution which is uh represented as
a cosal graph. So this okay given that
we don't have a um yeah we don't we do
not have uh I I mean we do not have
information of the true uh posterior
distribution of this causal state
transition. We actually resolve to uh
using a variational biian optimization
approach here where we compute an
approximate distribution by minimizing
the KL divergence which actually can be
formulated as maximizing the evidence
lower bound. So that's this G expression
here and that's how we actually
formulated the uh you know cosal graph
computation problem and also at the
transmit side there is also the problem
of computing the semantic states that is
achieved as so that is formulated as
maximizing the integrated information
conveyed by the cosal state about the uh
no yt which is the corresponding to the
inference variable at the receiver side
subjected through constraints on the
bandwidth. So how much information this
sett conveys about ST should be less
than or equal to some threshold. So that
actually tells about the bandwidth
constraint. So there are two different
problems here. So we solved these two
problems by formulating this uh cosal
graph uh as well as this yeah cosal
graph as well as the semantic
representation using neural gener
generative a based neural networks
wherein specifically cosal for cosal
graph we used a graph neural network
conserved and for semantic state
representation
um for semantic state representation
uh we actually used variational
autoenccoder based uh framework work to
represent that and we actually solve
this two two-level optimization problem
by a nested optimization uh using
gradient descent. So that's how we
actually solve the parameters of the
neural network. I won't go into the
details of uh yeah details of the
problem uh solution. So instead I would
like to further state certain simulation
results that we had. So first is uh what
we showed through this generative a
based uh framework is that or the welder
model based framework as I discussed
here is that um we actually showed that
compared to classical uh maximum
likelihood based transition modeling our
proposed causal semantic communication
system uh can better represent the
network state uh for all yeah for uh
diverse SNR uh ranges compared to
classical communic classical systems and
also we showed that we showed the
generalizability by considering that
okay so we started with some particular
uh network or autonomous agent
environment then after around let's say
6k samples we actually um changed the
environment dynamics then we actually
saw that the classical systems will take
you know the traditional system which
are basically datadriven a based
algorithms like enco I mean transformer
based encoder or decoder that takes
large amount of time to actually recur
back to the normal state but our
causality based system is able to adapt
quickly to this uh network dynamics. So
that's the that actually proves the
dynamic ad adaptability aspect. Uh yeah
so that actually concludes my work on
coal semantic communication for uh
digital twin based um systems.
Further I would like to quickly discuss
some future perspectives. Uh so as I
mentioned uh currently I have been
considering only a pointto-point
semantic communication system. So my uh
next goal is to actually construct
multi-user semantic communication system
um wherein okay so these set of uses are
okay this could be robots or um humans.
So they or a combination of them. So
they are actually encouraged in solving
a particular uh maybe a short task or a
uh or distant task it can be. So therein
the objective is to design a joint
communication and control system. So
herein we can consider that each of
these user has access to only a partial
observation. So basically a case of
partial observable marco marco decision
process. So that way we can actually
formulate that. So using this partial
observation and also using the
communicated information from other uses
each user should form a world model
about the environment. Um yeah then the
quality of the using the world model
that they construct they come up with a
shared semantic language or shared
symbol system. U yeah so that actually
will depend upon the quality of the
welder model learned by each of the
uses. So here a promising approach is to
actually use the perception and action
planning framework design a perception
and action planning framework through
active inference
concept. So in this direction uh yeah so
I'm actually looking at uh formulating
the semantic encoder or causal
representation frameworks as follows. So
let's say we have a semantic encoder at
semantic encoder. So that is defined as
an approximate distribution which is Q
of UT where U is the semantic symbol and
isert T K correspond to the cosal states
um pursued at different uses where K
corresponds to user index and then cosal
representation at each user we can
actually consider it as Q of isk given
is t minus one UT minus one and here o
tk corresponds to the partial
observation at user k and yt minus1k
corresponds to the inference decision in
the previous time slot uh at for for for
user k so here observation basically
it's like composed of two aspect one is
like the partial observation and also
like the inference decision that this
particular age user will uh make yeah so
so basically the causal representation
or the the world the world model
actually changes uh based on the
inference decisions of each user. Um and
yeah, sematic symbol prior priorities P
of UT and then the logical reasoning and
observation model we can actually
formulate it like probability of YT + 1
given is T time probability of OT given
YT is a T. So observation depends on
inference decision as well as the causal
state and then the actual transition
model will be as is shown here. Uh yeah.
So here um yeah so actually motivated by
the formulations in this uh recent paper
um that appeared in RK we can actually
formulate uh the collective u free
energy based uh yeah we can actually
write the collective free energy for
this particular um obser yeah but a
particular multi-user semantic
communication system um so yeah so
wherein I'm not going to the details of
this mathematical expression but we can
um write this free energy as consisting
of three different factors. So one is
the reconstruction aspect. So how much
the user can actually reconstruct the
observations based on the uh cosal world
model. And then the second term is
actually corresponding to the um cosal
dynamics approximation which means how
much the user use each user can
approximate the cosal um ve model based
on the observations partial observation
at its end. Um and the final factor will
be corresponding to the uh a time that
actually regularizes the entropy of
semantic encoder which actually means
that so this this time would be actually
corresponding to the um to minimizing
certain communication cost. So or
basically uh ensuring that we
communicate minimal semantic semantics
from the data. Yeah. So we can actually
formulate two um phase like an active
inference. we can actually um formulate
the free energy expressions for the
perception phase and also for the
inference phase which is corresponding
to yeah where y corresponds to the
inference variable and yeah so then the
objective is basically um using the u
yeah the free energy for the perception
part we can actually compute the
minimalistic semantic encoder or the
common semantic symbol system as well as
using the inference uh free energy
framework we can actually um compute the
best inference decision that each user
should make using its own causal uh
state perception as well as the
communicated information. So that's the
you know that's the framework um that I
think can be applied for this multi-user
semantic communication systems. Uh yeah
so that will yeah with that I will
conclude my talk. So as I uh mentioned
um 5G could not meet all the promises.
Um however as we move towards next
generation system wherein uh our yeah so
the communication networks are not just
about building better um
um wireless I mean better um standard I
mean better systems which high data rate
or low latency and so on but also
incorporating aspects like sensing or
trustworthiness or and also autonomous
control of uh distant agents So cyber
physical system. So we should transition
to a telecom brain based vision which is
consist of consisting of modules like
sensing, perception, world model and
action planning. And I discuss in detail
few of our work on semantic
communication where we actually showed
that using causality and neurosyolic AI
we can actually build minimalistic
generalizable and high fidelity semantic
system. So they're saving a lot of the
bandwidth. Uh and then yeah the future
research vision uh my future research
vision is centered around building
sustainable trustworthy and socially
responsible next ngi native wireless
systems using this telecom principles.
Yeah. So with that I will conclude my
talk and if you have any questions I am
um glad to uh answer those.
Thank you for the awesome presentation.
Okay, I will prepare my questions and
also welcome anyone in the chat to write
and just while I crop and prepare that
just could you share a little bit h how
did you come to be setting up the lab
like just what was your trajectory from
through school on through here? How did
you get into this research area?
Uh yeah so I did my PhD in um you know
fifth generation wireless communications
uh with focus on the physical layer
aspects like you know building uh
developing uh beam forming solutions or
channel estimation schemes using
conventional signal processing
algorithms like know specifically even
approximate bias inference kind of
techniques.
um uh yeah so those are th those are my
main focus during my PhD but when I
transition to a postdoal position I
choose a different path like I mean I
yeah I saw that you know uh the physical
layer advancements is kind of you know
all the physical literature is kind of
saturating out so we need some new
revolution
uh in communication system as we move
towards next generation systems that
that can Yeah, that can be
um feasible by the incorporation of AI
but not just you know datadriven AI but
um a that can actually reason like human
beings. So that's so that is the
motivation why I started to work with uh
professor valid sad on um this
particular topic. Um yeah so that's how
I actually entered into know semantic
communications
uh which is actually a revolutionary
approach that u uh that is aimed at
build and improving the resource
efficiency of future communication
systems. Um so yeah so that's that's how
I ended up at this um this particular
research. Thank you. Well I'm extremely
um appreciative to your colleagues and
you for bringing this all together and
and I'm excited to see where this all
heads um because it's aligned with many
of my interests and I also believe it's
it's a critical infrastructure kind of
civilizational technology layer. So
first I tried to summarize in one
sentence because there are so many
pieces and so many formalisms that might
be new. So my one sentence summary was
dynamics and constraints of semantic
transfer in hybrid and synthetic network
intelligence
systems. And then to kind of expand on
that a little bit. So I'll just make a
remark about where I saw active
inference coming into play and and some
of the um important areas. So um you
starting with a diatic model uh
templated diatic communication models
like teacher apprentice or adversarial
models.
You are looking towards using active
inference to allow real-time cooperation
and turn taking in multi- aent systems
and that would allow the embodiment
which is achieved in in
different engineering solutions in
different ways. However, the top-down
approach is what is the analytical
formalism that gives a a unity from a um
modeling perspective to all of these
different engineering approaches. And
those formalisms that you presented on
allow the embodiment of agent or
situation, class, instance, and context
specific cognitive mechanisms and
dynamics which broadly correspond to
perception on the inbound and action
selection. and in and on the outbound
with reasoning happening in between. And
so what that is heading towards is a a
first principles approach that applies
to semantic dynamics which could be used
within a singlethreaded shared database
state multi- aent system. So it could be
a a system with a very specific
logistical order or known computational
resource constraints all the way on
through nested arbitrary systems and
then importantly embodied cyberphysical
networks where there can be the explicit
introduction of physical and energy
models, bandwidth and resource costs.
And so that brings a complimentary view
from the engineering side onformational
and cognitive constraints with important
physical constraints of the
everchanging basis of networks.
So, just kind of wanted to echo back
because there were so many important
pieces in the talk and it was a lot of
information and it's a part of our tech
stack that just kind of works like the
phone just has service and it's really
abstracted and then of course we know
that the phones are coming out with
different versions and I'm not
knowledgeable in these areas that much
but it's like services different in
different regions and things change and
and and technology happens like that. So
giving that kind of view into the tech
stack is also I think really critical.
So usually I do not give a sort of
extended comment but there's just I was
writing know so many notes. So do you
have any thoughts or ideas on on that?
Yeah I think you have uh described I
mean the summary of this talk and yeah
quite well u I mean that that's a great
summary. Um so yeah so one point just to
uh conclude is that like you know uh so
right now with with 5G we are able to
get you know large download speeds or um
um lower latency you know streaming and
so on. Uh but you know the but when we
actually move to a next generation
system it's not just about cellular
communication. So the network should
also you know we should be able to build
much more smarter environments like you
know smarter transportation systems or
smarter uh you know industries uh teley
health systems. So that actually recurs
the network to actually um have a
perception about the physical world. I
mean if the network has to know uh
control the operations of these uh
distant autonomous agents
uh um so yeah so the network should have
a u accurate perception about the
physical world um unlike in classical
system where uh you know we just treat
the communication systems just like a
passive passive system. So whatever
message comes in you just objective is
just to communicate that uh messages
with you know um high accuracy at the
receiving end. Uh yeah so so that's so
that's a transitional
um paradigm that you know we are looking
at as we move towards 6G or uh yeah 6G
and beyond. Yeah, another area I wanted
to remark on and and part of that
transformation is predictive processing
and the role of prediction in
compression. So the predictive
processing frame differencing is used in
standard syntax informationdriven
compressive systems like frame
differencing in a video. If all you have
to do is transmit what changes between
frames, it gives a uh within a given
local minima of minimal compression and
that was discovered in the computer
science area and then actually entered
into this broader discussion about like
visual and sensory systems. So that's
using frame differencing to for example
transmit a 4K video with less syntactic
information flow. And then actually it
goes even further with all of your work
exploring the transfer in a latent or
semantic space which could be more like
a primary lexical semantics or
conceptual modularity all the way up on
through possibly complex pragmatics like
action
directives or or complex information
being shared at at a higher semantic
level. And then that's kind of again
where active inference comes into play
is having a unified framework that on
one hand can give an account for why
frame differencing at a purely sensory
kind of Shannon information level is a
compressive strategy and then use on a
latent space in exactly analogous
formalism a co-operative mechanism to
enable semantic compression. So like if
if we both have a friend ABC, but we
both know them as A, then there's the
question of the bits per second of the
audio transfer, like how good is my
microphone and how much data needs to be
sent. But maybe a given bandwidth, you
only need to say A because B and C are
semantically known. And so that just
kind of shows like it's not just about
the amount of data transmitted.
compressing it, all other things being
equal is is good. Why send extra data
through the wire? But now, and this is
kind of where I want to hear your
thoughts on this. We see a lot of work
with natural language
intermediaries and that is used to
transfer information broadly with this
kind of natural language interface. Um,
but also we could imagine situations
where semantic information transfer
happens on networks. And I think this is
exactly what you were getting at. So
what kinds of information can be
transferred? Like does transmitting
vector
embeddings have a marketkedly
different
semantic impact than for example
dialogue between
LLM like the kinds of bandwidth that are
currently being used in natural language
mediated transmission. Could strategies
like multimodal or semantic compression
give some kind of order of magnitude
modifications in the bandwidth or the
impact of communication amongst latent
space.
Uh yeah so yeah so one way to look at is
like okay so let's say if you have like
know two LLM agents communicating
um and let's say okay so they're using
this natural language to communicate
among them um so yeah so
um yeah so so I let's let's say okay so
in in semantic communication
um so we are not I mean so so we are not
really concerned about uh you know how
the how LM agent one communicates in a
you know grammatically correct
um English sentence uh know with all the
details included to LLM agent 2 rather
we will be more more uh interest yeah we
are actually our frameworks actually
lead to okay following this um emerging
language formulation
um so as time progresses what these LLM
agents would uh learn is that okay let's
say they're still communicating using
English uh letters um so they end up
learning a language um okay
communicating a sequence of words or
letters
uh that is sufficient enough for the
other agent to know understand it I mean
it need not be you know it can be
considered like a machine machine
language which need not be perfect like
an English language But no but certain
sequence of letters that is enough for
LLM agent 2 to actually understand LLM
agent one given the background knowledge
that agent each agent has um like you
know LLM agent one so okay so when when
we when two humans actually start
communicating okay when when two new uh
um yeah so when uh one when I start
communicating to another person whom I
don't know before so initially there is
lot of overhead like you know we have to
introduce ourselves we have to share
some background knowledge about uh
ourselves. Um so then further as they
become friends so then when they
communicate so they they have a lot of
know implicit assumptions about um the
other person how that person would be
thinking or how that person would be um
viewing the world around him. So the
communication would actually be more um
no more optimized for optimized
considering all also that background
right. So similar to that so yeah so if
two LLM's agent two LLM agents
communicate among them so so using an
emerging language framework our
objective is to build a machine language
that is sufficient enough
for LLM agent to pursue or understand
what LLM agent one actually means. So
there is so that kind of a machine
language construction uh leads to a
better usage of know communication
resources. Um so does yeah does that
make sense to you? Yes. Like where that
kind of takes me is when we're talking
about emergent semantics and pragmatics
which could be between family members,
it could be between strangers, humans,
it could be online or in person. It
could be two LLMs, it could be a person
LM, like every kind of combo.
Um, having this approach gives a way to
scaffold theformational
dynamics and kind of separate out the
syntactic layer from the semantic layer.
And then it naturally leads to these
kinds of uh
sustained
duration semantic learning strategies.
Like if every single message was coming
from a different source, then there
would be some sort of like no free
lunch, but you could take the best
semantics as possible to each fresh
source. Like if it was just a different
every single time. But then to the
extent that you can have a um prior
about a given type of interaction all
the way on through the most specific
prior which is exact relational with a
given other entity then that allows
semantic communication strategies like
one means this dinner and two means that
dinner. Well then they only have to send
one letter. And then when we get into
these situations where it can be machine
machine semantics then that's kind of
what tokens are like that's why words in
a given language get truncated up into
these essentially probabilistically
determined semantic units like oh it's
this verb and then ed to be the past
tense. So it's like or whatever the
tokenization strategy happens to
be and then how do you use your tokens
to have this no regret or minimal regret
best possible token conveyance
linearity to
finesse the translation of elements of a
semantic space which could be static or
dynamic into a linearized sequence of
messages. And then the network
perspective is really important because
network properties can matter. Like if
you have a network where 100% of packets
are delivered, you're going to have c
certain kinds of strategic constraints
in communication. Whereas if you have a
network where a given percent are being
at this you know redirected or this kind
of etc is happening like those physical
constraints do matter for a
communication strategy and so having a
sort of
integrated analytic approach to
modeling explicit syntax constraints
classical Shannon syntax entropydriven
computer science and networking
on through
abstract cognitive informationational
constraints like we're just going to
assume that it could be the maximally
informative symbol like the letter
distribution in natural language could
be made more informative. So using some
rebalanced even A through Z, there could
be increased information
transfer, but that would only be in
certain situations like a machine
machine situation might be able to do
that kind of hacking into the actual
symbols being set in plain text. But
that just again reflects on how there's
both the particular network and symbol
set constraints that are really really
well laid out from a Shannon syntax
approach.
And then there's this outer space which
we're still just beginning to explore
that is grounded in the
primary symbol entropy and the
observations. However, it can have
multiple layers of cognitive and
metacognitive dynamics which are not so
closely bound to the
primary Shannon constraints but still do
have imported constraints of their own.
However, that's what semantic
information is about because semantics
can be about semantics. I think that was
one of the questions on one of the
slides which is like cognition on
cognition or metacognition.
Yeah. So it's it's like a no above this
communication constraints that we have
we are effectively forming a semantic
layer between the transmitter and
receiver which is actually know
constrained by all this cognitivity
um yeah and then the understanding
uh aspects right
yeah that's very insightful I mean
discussion
thank you yeah well just in sort of
closing, what are your next steps or
what are like the timeline with the lab
or how would people learn more or get
involved?
Um yeah, so um yeah, I'll be starting my
uh new position from August uh
2025 and yeah, I'm uh looking to recruit
one to two PhD students. Um so yeah and
also know continue this work with the
students on this particular topic and I
yeah I mean I do have a uh lab website
which is still kind of under
construction but you know I can share
this I mean I will share all my updates
through this website. Um yeah awesome.
Yeah happy to uh discuss further or even
know give a talk later when when I have
more results. Yeah. Cool. Well,
again, very appreciative of of the work
and the concise
presentation. Wish you the best. Till
next time. Thank you very much. Thank
you for the invitation. Bye bye.